We have learned about the Merge sort.
Now let's implement the Merge sort algorithm in sea language and later on in the next video, we are
going to sort of exercise that boom and the merge sort of algorithm in Java.
So we start by including the S, the IOC search and now merging two sub arrays and into editing.
So this is the method that starts by merging the two arrays, submarines and into array or OK, so it
took meet their array.
Air that integer B and the integer Q and the integer off we start.
Creating the L separate from a at Index B do a index Q and creating a separate M from a Index Q Plus
want to index on.
So we have here we have created.
This out of we have divided it.
And to P and Q, you and I, so we have to and this is here.
The P that Q and I know this is the left.
This is the L subreddit and this is the sub.
This is what we have created.
We create and one equal Q minus B plus one and two equal R minus Q.
These are the indices that we are going to use.
So al at index M one and M and and two.
For that, we create the entire equal to zero i less than N1 and A-plus.
Plus we create L.
At index equal to array at index, B-plus, I and in another loop that starts from equal to zero and
j less than M2 and J + +.
So we create we assign the values of Index J equal to a rate at Index Q plus one plus J.
These are two separate.
It's very, very important.
They are not nested.
They are all standalone loops.
So they are not.
OK.
The second step is maintained the current index of sub arrays and main array.
And I, J and K three.
Variables are equal to zero, equal to zero, and K equals to be the third step until we reach either
end of either L or pick the larger among elements L and and place them in the correct position at a.
Index from B to R.
So while i less than and j less than N2, so i less than N1 and j less than +2.
If L at index i less than or equal and index j then make a rank equal and index i and increase i + +.
Otherwise, it will make a rate at index equal at then this j and increase J + + other and in all cases,
increase the K + +.
Now.
When we run out of elements in either and pick up the remaining elements and put in a at index B to
us.
So while I less than anyone.
Array at Index Gate Equal, Ray and I so while I has been a no on increase, I buy one by one and close
this loop.
Wild J less than and two.
So we are comparing the I for N1 and J with related with N to while j less than M to array at Index
K equal at Index J and J + + + +.
Then we divide the array into subsidies and sort them and merge them.
We create that method.
Merge sort that took into the parameters that I read that we are going to sort that into and are if
l less, then are is the point where the array is divided into sub to two sub arrays.
So this is the middle L plus l minus R over to the merge sort.
We called the method that we have created here.
This is that occurred near recursion.
We best array and and.
OK.
So.
Merge, sort again, we call this and this merger sort.
We have seen this in their algorithm.
How to ride the algorithm, so please go back to the previous video in order to see why we are calling
this the times.
This is AL and this is embarrassing.
The Parametres here AMC+ one and the odd because we have divided into two sub two sub arrays, we have
best the first and the here is the second sound editing.
OK.
Now merged the sort the sub raised by calling them the merge that we have created before.
So this method will merge the two subcategories and I'm an.
OK.
The the that we have created this method many times, it's a just a lot that go through all the elements
of the action.
Now a driver program, yesterday we create an array and the mean we get the size of this array by making
size equal size of a tray at over size of the next zero.
And we use the Amersfoort method that we have created here in order to.
To America, the sort.
Merge sort of this at today and with print assorted array by using the print array.
In this video, we have learned how to merge sort in sea language and in next video, we are going to
implement and test this code in Java.
So the same syntax, the same algorithm will be implemented.
So I need from you to to memorize this.
This kind of sorting this is very complex.
I know this.
I have difficulty with Amersfoort when I was making when I was making that at university exams and interviews.
And this is a very complex sorting, but it's very simple if you understand it step by step and repeat
the videos and the till mastering this.
So in my, in my opinion, this is the best.
Sorting and the complex sort and the most complex sorting algorithm in all of search on all the.